do you think that human beings have like
a heightened aesthetic capacity than any
other creature we know I mean is that
yeah is that safe to assume yeah I mean
that we have we have examples of certain
creatures that we can see pay very close
attention to aesthetics in certain
contexts okay but it's a very limited
context yeah you know so we have
bowerbirds yeah that you know build
these elaborate strange Walters - nobody
knows what and if there's one thing we
can say it's that the female bowerbirds
are paying very close attention to
details they must be very critical so it
must be like let's take like an
exceedingly critical female to cause a
male to go to those legs well it gives
me great pleasure to say this next link
to you better I think there there are
cases and probably if you were to look
for places you know there's this
postmodern view that science is all
garbage dug by the fact that it's been
overwhelmingly practiced in the West by
white men yeah and that that means that
effectively the content is biased and
this is has almost no truth to it with
something like the periodic table which
there's not there's nothing good about
the fact that it was you know elucidated
by primarily white men but the point is
what they elucidate it was actually true
so it would have been elucidated by
whoever did the elucidating in biology
because the complexity is so high and
the questions are so strange there is
actually room for us to have missed
things because people with certain
backgrounds did the studying and their
biases cause them to overlook the
darndest stuff and so I do think there's
a way in which you know we look at
bowerbirds
and because it has been largely male
evolutionary biologists trying to do the
explaining there's been this bizarre
tendency to - you know ok why are the
males do this crazy behavior
well the females required of them well
what are the females require to them you
know who knows females you know a heck
and it's not true I think that we will
very shortly
come to understand that these females
have been absolutely obsessed about
something that is so important but hard
to elucidate so we've missed why you
know the peacock looks the way it does
we know that it's because the female
requires the peacock to do this display
or she won't make but what we haven't
gotten to is why the females require
this and why all of these systems in
which females require males to
demonstrate some very unusual capacity
have evolved the way they do and I think
the Shocker is going to be that there
was no frivolousness and what these
females were requiring of males at all
this was not a aesthetic choice for its
own purpose this aesthetic choice was
Nature's Way of asking deep questions
about what that male's genome was
capable of enduring in the future and
when we come to see that I believe we
will have a good laugh over the fact
that yes indeed male evolutionary
biologists overlook the obvious for an
awful long time